<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IPAM 2018 Workshop</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on IPAM 2018 Workshop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data and Plots</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/r-data-import/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/r-data-import/</guid>
      <description>Datasets R comes with many datasets built in. These are part of the datasets package that is always loaded in R. For example, the mtcars dataset is a well-known dataset from Motor Trend magazine, documenting fuel consumption and vehicle characteristics for a number of vehicles. At the R console, typing mtcars will print the entire dataset.
You can find help on datasets as usual using the Help tab in RStudio, clicking on the Packages link and navigating to the datasets package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Cox Regression</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-dhcox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-dhcox/</guid>
      <description>Introduction It is only a short way from the toy MLE example to a more useful example using Cox regression.
But first, we need the survival package.
if (!require(&amp;quot;survival&amp;quot;)) { stop(&amp;quot;this vignette requires the survival package&amp;quot;) } We generate some simulated data for the purpose of this example. We will have three sites each with patient data (sizes 1000, 500 and 1500) respectively, containing
 sex (0, 1) for male/female age between 40 and 70 a biomarker bm a time to some event of interest an indicator event which is 1 if an event was observed and 0 otherwise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed and Privacy-Preserving Computations in R</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/</guid>
      <description>Balasubramanian Narasimhan
Department of Biomedical Data Sciences and Department of Statistics
Stanford University
Abstract The R programming environment provides a rich suite of methods and algorithms for statistical model fitting and computation in general. The exploratory interface of R makes it an ideal platform for prototyping, analyzing and deploying new algorithms in an open and extensible manner. This tutorial will begin with a short self-contained introduction to R and its package mechanism for programming extensions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homomorphic Computations</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-intro/</guid>
      <description>A homomorphism is a structure-preserving map from one algebraic structure to another; see Wikipedia. Privacy experts are interested in homomorphic computation because it offers a way to perform computations on encrypted data, either in a distributed setting or in the cloud, thereby handling many of the headaches associated with storing/moving/anonymizing data. Homomorphic computation also finds application in secure voting, verifyable computing etc.
A homomorphic encryption scheme is one that provides such a homomorphism along with the infrastructure to carry out the computations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lasso on Vertically Partitioned Data</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/vertical-partitioned-lasso/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/vertical-partitioned-lasso/</guid>
      <description>Implementing Lasso on vertically partitioned data in a naive fashion provides some information on the issues with vertically partitioned data.
Consider a dataset with response \(y\) where the predictor matrix \(X\) is vertically partitioned among three sites.
\[ X = [X_1, X_2, X_3] \]
where the combined \(X\) is \(n\times p\), each \(X_i\) is \(n\times p_k\), for \(k= 1, 2, 3\), and \(\sum_{i=1}^3 p_k = p.\)
We wish to fit a lasso model:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poisson MLE via Homomorphic Computation</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-mle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-mle/</guid>
      <description>Introduction We present a toy example of a homomorphic computation involving maximum likelihood estimation.
Consider the following data motivated by an example from the mle function in the stats4 R package: we wish to estimate \(\lambda\), the Poisson parameter \(\lambda\) for randomly generated count data y below:
library(stats4) set.seed(17822) y &amp;lt;- rpois(n = 40, lambda=10) # Easy one-dimensional MLE: nLL &amp;lt;- function(lambda) -sum(stats::dpois(y, lambda, log = TRUE)) fit0 &amp;lt;- mle(nLL, start = list(lambda = 5), nobs = NROW(y)) The function nLL is the negative log-likelihood of the data and the function mle computes the maximum likelihood estimate that can be printed out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Preserving Homomorphic Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/homomorphing-regression/</guid>
      <description>Problem Setup This example, based on the homomorpheR package, was communicated to me by Kee Siong Ng.
 FIU holds the response vector y RE1 holds the data x[, 1:3] RE2 RE2 holds the data x[,4]  Together, they want to learn a linear model to predict y using x but in such a way that
 nobody sees each other’s data, RE1 holds the coefficients for the variables it holds, which is not visible to others RE2 holds the coefficients for the variables it holds, which is not visible to others Prediction of a new instance requires the collaboration of RE1 and RE2  FIU first generates a public-private key pair using the Paillier scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Intro to R</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/r-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/r-tour/</guid>
      <description>About the R language, briefly If you are used to traditional computing languages, you will find R different in many ways. The basic ideas behind R date back four decades (to the S language of Chambers, Becker and Wilks] and have a strong flavor of exploration: one can grapple with data, understand its structure, visualize it, summarize it etc. Therefore, a common way people use R is by typing a command and immediately see the results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RStudio IDE</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/r-studio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/r-studio/</guid>
      <description>We can only cover some important aspects of RStudio here. There are a number of resources online, including Youtube videos that you can consult.
When you start RStudio, you will get a view similar to what is shown below with perhaps slight differences.
One can type commands directly into the console window and see results. For example, go ahead and type 1+1 to use R as a calculator and see the result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Set up R Development Tools</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/setup-r-dev/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/setup-r-dev/</guid>
      <description>Components A complete programming and development environment requires the installation of
 R system, C/C++ compilers, TeX and friends.   Compilers Compilers are freely available for Windows and Macs; see the FAQs for windows and Macs on CRAN. Be sure to use the toolchains provided on CRAN rather than something on the net.
 MacOS requires installation of Xcode along with the command line tools via xcode --select.
 Windows requires the installation of the RTools package provided by CRAN.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Set up R and RStudio</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/setup-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/setup-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction R language implementations are freely available for Macs and Windows and and can be installed from any of the CRAN (Comprehensive R Archive Network) mirrors. RStudio is an IDE (Integrated Development Environment) for R and is also available in a free version.
Go to the CRAN website and download it for your Mac or PC. (We assume no one is using Linux; if you are that advanced, then you already know what to do!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vertically Partitioned Data</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/vertical-partitioned-logistic-ridged/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/vertical-partitioned-logistic-ridged/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Li et al. (2016) implement a logistic regression using vertically partitioned data.
They consider the (ridged) model:
\[ \begin{array}{ll} \underset{\beta}{\mbox{minimize}} &amp;amp; \sum_{i=1}^n \log{(1+exp(-Y_i{\mathbf \beta X_i})} + \frac{\lambda}{2} ||\beta||_2^2. \end{array} \]
To solve this problem in the vertically partitioned setting, they exploit two facts.
The gram matrix for the global problem is a sum of the gram matrices for each partition:  \[ K = XX^T = \sum_{i=1}^K X_iX_i^T \]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPAM 2018 Tutorial</title>
      <link>/post/tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tutorial/</guid>
      <description>R-related Stuff  Set up R and RStudio Set up Development Tools Optional Quick Tour of RStudio A drive-by summary of R   Two R Packages  OpenCPU allows one to call R over a REST API. Convex Optimization in R provides a Domain Specific Language for Convex Optimization.   Applications  Distributed Computation on Horizontally Partitioned Data We discuss an open approach for distributed computing using the distcomp (see Narasimhan et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>